<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="converters">
  <properties>
    <title>Theme Converters</title>
  </properties>

  <body>
    <section>
      <title>Theme Converters</title>
      <p>
        Skin Look And Feel supports GTK and KDE skins. These theme
        engines provide support for most of the components of Swing. 
      </p>
      <p>
        Since the beginning, the choice was made to not create SkinLF
        own skin format but to reuse existing. Adding support for new
        theme engines is one of the goal of the next SkinLF
        versions. Meanwhile, end-users want to get new themepacks to
        include in their application and to be able to create such
        themepacks easily. Here come converters. A converter will
        <i>convert</i> a skin in a specific format in a theme pack
        using GTK and KDE engines.
      </p>
      <section>
        <title>Abstract Converter</title>
        <p>
        </p>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>MS Visual Style Converter</title>
        <p>
          Windows XP ships with the ability to theme the user
          interface. It comes with the default Windows XP style aka
          Luna. Themes in Windows XP are called Visual Styles. They
          are binary files containing the images used to paint the
          various components along with theme description files (in
          xml).
        </p>
        <p>
          There are tools to create such themes. One of the tool we
          are going to use is StyleBuilder from <a
          href="http://www.tgtsoft.com/">tgtsoft</a>. StyleBuilder
          knows how to extract the images and resource files from the
          Visual Styles.
        </p>
        <p>
          The converter migrates StyleBuilder-extracted Microsoft
          Visual Styles to SkinLF themepacks. The conversion is not
          straightforward and requires some preparation but it kinds
          of work.
        </p>
        <p>
          First step is to find a Visual Style to convert. There are
          multiple at <a
          href="http://www.themexp.org">ThemeXP.org</a>. Then the
          theme has to be extracted using StyleBuilder. Once
          extracted, the converter can be invoked to create the
          themepack.
        </p>
      </section>
    </section>
  </body>
</document>
