<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article id="tutorial-msstyle">
  <properties>
    <title>Converting a Microsoft Visual Style to a SkinLF themepack</title>
  </properties>

  <body>
    <section>
      <title>Converting a Microsoft Visual Style to a SkinLF themepack</title>
      <p>
        I've been asked by a user how to convert a Microsoft Visual
        Style to SkinLF. My first answer was: <i>you have to get the
        source code to get the converter, then to use StyleBuilderXP
        to extract the visual style, it generates an XML file along
        with a couple of BMP files, you run the converter on the xml,
        then there are final steps to perform by hand.</i> I do not
        know if the user manages to create its own SkinLF themepack
        but I promess he will get a tutorial on creating a themepack
        from a visual style so here it is.
      </p>
      <section>
        <title>Step 1 - Find the Visual Style</title>
        <p>
          There are several sites hosting visual styles, go to one of
          them and grab a visual style:
          <ul>
            <li><a href="http://www.themexp.org">ThemeXP.org</a></li>
            <li><a href="http://skins.deviantart.com/visualstyle/">deviantART</a></li>
            <li><a href="http://www.studiotwentyeight.com/">StudioTwentyEight</a></li>
            <li><a href="http://www.aqua-soft.org/">Aqua Soft</a></li>
          </ul>
        </p>
        <p>
          If your visual style comes in a ZIP file, unzip it. Once
          done, you should find a file ending with .msstyles
          extension.
          <note>
            If you plan to distribute your themepack, make sure to get
            the agreement of the Visual Style creator first.
          </note>
        </p>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>Step 2 - Extract the .msstyle</title>
        <p>
          Download and install the evaluation of StyleBuilder at <a
          href="http://www.tgtsoft.com/download.php">TGTSoft.com</a>. Start
          StyleBuilder. From the File menu, select "Import .msstyles
          file". In the popup window, select the .msstyles previously
          downloaded and a folder when the theme will be extracted
          (make sure the folder exists - I usually created a folder
          named "extracted" in the folder of the .msstyles). If the
          import goes fine, a window will ask whether you want to open
          the theme, say "Yes".
        </p>
        <p>
          In the "extracted" folder, you will find a bunch of files
          and folders. There are XML files describing the theme and
          png, bmp image files which are the actual pixmaps to paint
          the theme (as in a themepack, there is nothing new here).
        </p>
        <p>
          Some visual styles embed several variations of the same
          theme, in such case there will be several .xml files, one
          for each variation.
        </p>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>Step 3 - Converting to themepack</title>
        <p>
          The converters are bundled in the skinlf.jar. Most uptodate
          version is available when doing a checkout of the code from
          the CVS repository (See <a
          href="http://skinlf.dev.java.net">skinlf.dev.java.net</a>).
        </p>
        <p>
          To convert the visual style to a themepack, open a terminal
          from the "bin" folder of the SkinLF distribution and run:
          <pre class="code">
            java -cp skinlf.jar
            com.l2fprod.tools.msstyles.MsStylesToSkinLF
            &lt;path-to-the-visualstyle-folder&gt;
            &lt;path-to-the-visualstyle.xml&gt;
            &lt;path-to-the-themepack-folder-to-create&gt;
          </pre>
          In the target folder, it will generate the directory
          structure of a themepack including skinlf-themepack.xml,
          gtk, icons, kde.
        </p>
        <p>
          At this point, you should be able to get a preview of how
          your theme will look like. You can try it with the SkinLF
          demo:
          <pre class="code">
            demo.bat &lt;path-to-the-themepack-folder-to-create&gt;\skinlf-themepack.xml
          </pre>
        </p>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>Step 4 - Finalizing the themepack</title>
        <p>
          However, the theme might not be usable yet as the converter
          is not yet top-class converter. It does the basic and let
          you do the fine tuning of the theme, this way you become an
          artist :).
        </p>
        <p>
          The most common problems are:
          <ul>
            <li>Combobox looks bad</li>
            <li>Menu border is the default border</li>
            <li>Internal frame border is incorrect</li>
            <li>Some transparency issues with check or radio buttons</li>
            <li>Icons for FileChooser, Internal Frames are set to default</li>
            <li>Font size is set to default</li>
          </ul>
        </p>
        <section>
          <title>Combobox looks bad</title>
          <p>
            TODO
          </p>
        </section>
        <section>
          <title>Menu border is the default border</title>
          <p>
            TODO
          </p>
        </section>
        <section>
          <title>Internal frame border is incorrect</title>
          <p>
            TODO
          </p>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>Step 5 - Ready for prime time</title>
        <p>
          You have successfully created a new themepack. Make the
          community benefits from your effort by contributing the
          themepack to <a
          href="http://www.javootoo.com">javootoo.com</a>, send
          an email to <i>webmaster at javootoo.com</i>.
        </p>
      </section>
    </section>
  </body>
</article>
